<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Terraforms on Prasanth Janardhanan</title>
    <link>/terraform/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Terraforms on Prasanth Janardhanan</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Prasanth Janardhanan</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/terraform/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Creating an isolated cluster - provisioning a cluster and a Bastion host using Ansible</title>
      <link>/terraform/ansible-cloud-setup/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/terraform/ansible-cloud-setup/</guid>
      <description>This is the second part of the series on setting up a cluster using Terraform and Ansible. In the first part, we had set up the bare cluster Virtual Machines. The set up included a virtual private network, a bastion server, and a separately configurable cluster of nodes.
The nodes are ready but not software or configuration is done so far. In the next step, we will provision all the nodes in our cloud</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting up a Bastion host and a three-node cluster on Hetzner cloud using Terraform and Ansible</title>
      <link>/terraform/terraform-hetzner-cloud-setup-example/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/terraform/terraform-hetzner-cloud-setup-example/</guid>
      <description>Infrastructure as code has a great benefit - you can make a cluster available in a few minutes. Then, switch the configuration with a few updates to the configuration. If you ever had long hours staring at blinking LEDs while it installed from a stack of CDs, you will know what a relief this is.
Terraform makes it possible to declaratively create the cloud infrastructure, supports all major cloud providers, and is easy to learn if you can spare an afternoon.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
